Guide to the Jay B. Hubbell Papers, 1816-1998 and undated, bulk 1920-1979 RL.00581
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jay B. Hubbell papers
1816-1998 and undated, bulk 1920-1979
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hubbell, Jay B. (Jay Broadus), 1885-1979
RL.00581
10.2 Linear Feet
Professor of American literature, Duke University, Durham, N.C. The Jay B. Hubbell Papers span the years from 1816 to 1998, with the bulk of the material documenting Hubbell's career from his early student years in the 1920s until his death in 1979. The collection consists mainly of his professional papers, including correspondence with colleagues and literary figures, articles written by others at his request for the Jay B. Hubbell Center, printed materials inscribed to him and written by him, and unpublished manuscripts. The material chronicles the four decades of Hubbell's career as professor and critic, which he dedicated to the growth and development of American literature as a field of critical inquiry. Among the many significant correspondents or subjects of others' writings are Conrad Aiken, Gay Wilson Allen, Robert Frost, Clarence Gohdes, members of the Hubbell family, Ralph Leslie Rusk, Carl Sandburg, Allen Tate, Arlin Turner, and John Hall Wheelock. Other significant topics covered by the material include the founding of the Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography at Duke University, the study and teaching of literature from the American South, the activities of the faculty at Duke University, and the development of the American Literature Section of the Modern Language Association (MLA).
6375 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Jay B. Hubbell Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from Jay B. Hubbell in 1978, with additional materials received from Hubbell and other donors from 1979 to 2001.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1885 May 8 Born, Smyth County, Va.
1905 A.B., University of Richmond
1908 A.M., Harvard University
1915-1916 Assistant Professor of English, Southern Methodist University
1916-1919 Associate Professor, Southern Methodist University
1918 Married Lucinda Smith Attended Field Artillery Central Officers Training Camp, Camp Zachary, Taylor, Ky.
1921-1927 E. A. Lilly Professor of English and English Department Chair, Southern Methodist University, Tex.
1922 Published An Introduction to Poetry Ph.D., Columbia University
1924 Published Prairie Pegasus (editor)
1924-1926 Served as Group Chairman, American Literature Section, Modern Language Association
1924-1927 Editor, Southwest Review
1927-1954 Professor of American Literature, Duke University
1927 Published An Introduction to Drama
1928 Founded American Literature (journal)
1928-1954 Served as Chairman of the Board of Editors, American Literature
1929 Published first issue of American Literature Published The Enjoyment of Literature
1929-1930, 1932 Visiting Professor, Columbia University summer sessions
1936 Published American Life in Literature
1939 Served as Group Chairman, American Literature Section, Modern Language Association
1941 Published The Last Years of Henry Timrod, 1864-1867
1943-1948 Director of Graduate Studies, English Department, Duke University
1949 Visiting Professor, University of California at Los Angeles Served as Visiting Expert with the U. S. Forces in Austria on the American Literature Project, and Visiting Professor of American Literature, University of Vienna
1950 Served as Visiting Expert with the U. S. Forces in Austria on the American Literature Project, and Visiting Professor of American Literature, University of Vienna
1953 Served as Fulbright Professor of American Literature and Civilization, University of Athens, Greece
1954 Published The South in American Literature Retired from Duke University
1954-1955 Visiting Professor, University of Virginia
1955 Won Mayflower Award
1956 Served as Smith-Mundt Professor of American Literature, Hebrew University, Jerusalem Visiting Professor, Clemson University
1957-1958 Visiting Professor, Columbia University
1959 Delivered Eugenia Dorothy Blount Lamar Lectures, Mercer University
1960 Published Southern Life in Fiction
1961 Visiting Professor, University of Kentucky
1964 Inauguration of the Jay B. Hubbell Medallion by the American Literature Section of the Modern Language Association
1964-1967 Appointed Honorary Consultant in American Cultural History, Library of Congress
1965 Published South and Southwest
1967 Published Essays on American Literature in Honor of Jay B. Hubbell
1972 Published Who Are the Major American Writers?
1976 Founded Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography; David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
1979 Feb. 13 Died
1980 Lucinda Hubbell died
Collection Overview
The Jay B. Hubbell Papers span the years from 1816 to 1998, with the bulk of the material documenting Hubbell's career from his early student years in the 1920s until his death in 1979. The collection consists mainly of his professional papers, including correspondence with colleagues and literary figures, articles written by others at his request for the Jay B. Hubbell Center, printed materials inscribed to him and written by him, and unpublished manuscripts. The material chronicles the four decades of Hubbell's career as professor and critic, which he dedicated to the growth and development of American literature as a field of critical inquiry. Among the many significant correspondents or subjects of others' writings are Conrad Aiken, Gay Wilson Allen, Robert Frost, Clarence Gohdes, members of the Hubbell family, Ralph Leslie Rusk, Carl Sandburg, Allen Tate, Arlin Turner, and John Hall Wheelock. Other significant topics covered by the material include the founding of the Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography at Duke University, the study and teaching of literature from the American South, the activities of the faculty at Duke University, and the development of the American Literature Section of the Modern Language Association (MLA). The collection is divided into eight series: Biographical; Correspondence, Alphabetical; Correspondence by Date; Writings and Speeches; Subject Files; Teaching Abroad; Photographs; and Clippings.
The Biographical Data Series contains correspondence, manuscripts of his autobiographical writings, financial and legal documents, writings by his siblings, curriculum vitae, and obituaries, all of which chronicle Hubbell's life from his earliest years until his death.
The largest component of the collection contains correspondence from colleagues, former students, and literary figures. The Correspondence, Alphabetical Series consists of many letters from students and colleagues. The bulk of the correspondence gives shape to the nature and status of American literary studies in the early- to mid-twentieth century. In particular, the many letters exchanged among Hubbell, his colleagues, and his students provide insight into the routine professional life of this first pioneering generation of scholars. From job appointments to topics of scholarship, the letters uncover the kinds of professional interests and pressures that influenced the formation of American literary studies. Additional miscellaneous letters are arranged chronologically in the Correspondence by Date Series. These letters mainly represent single items from colleagues, publishers, and minor writers. The same topics are represented here as in the correspondence arranged alphabetically.
Jay B. Hubbell authored numerous articles and books throughout his career which contributed to the bibliography of American literary studies. Samples of such are located in the collection's Writings and Speeches Series. The series is divided into two subseries, the Writings by Hubbell Subseries and the Writings by Others Subseries. The Writings by Hubbell Subseries includes unpublished manuscripts, publication files consisting of correspondence with publishers and review clippings, and printed material consisting of article reprints and reviews. The Writings by Others Subseries contains articles and essays by Hubbell's colleagues and peers, as well as several essays that Hubbell collected on topics of interest to him. It also contains several memoirs which narrate the lives and influence of several key figures in the first generations of American literary scholars.
The Subject Files Series chronicles some of the major events, interests, and projects of Hubbell's career. His involvement with the Modern Language Association is represented by material filed in the General Files Subseries. Also included in this subseries is material concerning several of his institutional affiliations, including Clemson University, Columbia University, and Southern Methodist University (SMU). Hubbell's papers concerning his many professional projects can be found in the Projects Subseries, such as the Checklist of Manuscripts and the Center for Southern Studies. Information related to many of the subject files can be found throughout the collection, particularly in the Biographical Data and Correspondence Series.
Jay Hubbell dedicated a generous portion of his scholarly career to teaching and students. Besides his interest in different configurations and institutions for furthering learning and scholarship, Hubbell spent several years teaching abroad. The Teaching Abroad Series contains correspondence and incidentals concerning his service at universities in Vienna, Jerusalem, and Athens. This series includes materials which highlight Hubbell's experiences at the intersection of American foreign policy and university teaching, as Hubbell served as a Visiting Expert for the U.S. Army in Vienna as well as a quickly evacuated Visiting Professor in Jerusalem in 1956, during the Arab-Israeli conflict.
The Photographs Series includes photographs of Hubbell, family, and colleagues. The series includes portraits of Hubbell alone as well as with family.
The Clippings Series contains newspaper and journal clippings recording the many significant personal and professional events of Hubbell's life. The series also includes clippings about contemporary events, friends, and colleagues which Hubbell found noteworthy.
Hubbell's papers pertaining to English Department matters and committee assignments can be found in the Duke University Archives. The David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library at Duke University houses many related collections, particularly in the Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography: the records of American Literature; American Literary Manuscripts; and the Modern Language Association's American Literature Section and Southern Literature Discussion Group; and the papers of Gay Wilson Allen, Sacvan Berkovitch, Cathy Davidson, and Arlin Turner.
Scholars -- United States; Scholars -- Correspondence; College teachers as authors; American literature -- Southern States -- History and criticism; Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography; American literature -- Study and teaching; Aiken, Conrad; Allen, Gay Wilson, 1903-1995; Duke University -- Faculty; Gohdes, Clarence, 1901-1997; Modern Language Association of America. American Literature Section; Rusk, Ralph L. (Ralph Leslie), 1888-; Hubbell family; Turner, Arlin; Tate, Allen; Wheelock, John Hall, 1886-1978; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967; Hubbell, Jay B. (Jay Broadus), 1885-1979; Frost, Robert, 1874-1963
- Biographical Data Series 1906-1980 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  The bulk of this series contains correspondence and financial documents (contract and royalty letters) chronicling the scope of Hubbell's career. The series also includes rough drafts of Hubbell's autobiographical writings, which seem to have been written largely at the end of his life, about his early years in rural Virginia, his early readings, and his years at Harvard University and Columbia University. His brother Paul Edgar Hubbell's writings, poems and an essay with a foreword by Jay B. Hubbell, as well as his sister Ruth Ann Hubbell's poetry are a part of the series. Folders arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Autobiographical Writings, 1947 and undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Contracts, 1926-1965 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence by Date, 1906-1979, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1920s-circa 1978 and undated (Box 1)
  - Hubbell, Paul Edgar, 1914-1977 (Box 1)
  - Hubbell, Ruth Ann, 1959-1978 and undated (Box 1)
  - Obituaries, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Printed Materials, 1918-1973 and undated (Box 2)
  - Royalties, 1930-1975 and undated (Box 2)
- Correspondence, Alphabetical Series, 1871-1979 and undated (bulk 1919-1970)
  Conditions Governing Access note
  [RESTRICTED. Contains letters of reference. For a period of 75 years after the latest date in the collection, patrons must sign an Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form before using materials.]
  This series contains letters from colleagues, students, publishers, and literary figures. Highlights of the correspondence include letters exchanged with Gay Wilson Allen, George Bond, Herbert Brown, Matthew Bruccoli, Mary Sue Carlock, John Chapman, James Emanuel, Benjamin F. Fisher, Herbert Gambrell, Clarence Gohdes, Theodore Gross, Ima Honaker Herron, Hugh Holman, Howard Mumford Jones, Lewis Leary, Maureen C. Mabbott, Rayburn Moore, Albert Robbins, Henry Nash Smith, Hope Stoddard, and Edward Stone. The series also includes correspondence with major literary figures and critics, such as B. A. Botkin, Donald Davidson, Robert Frost, Hamlin Garland, Ellen Glasgow, John Lomax, Howard Odum, Carl Sandburg, Allen Tate, and John Hall Wheelock. Many of the letters to literary figures concern permissions and copyrights, as Hubbell edited several anthologies. His letters exchanged with colleagues and students include professional concerns such as recommendations and references, exams, job opportunities, departmental procedures, and the study of American Literature. The largest group of letters is from the poet John Hall Wheelock, dating from 1921 when Hubbell wrote asking permission to use Wheelock's poem, "Earth," in a poetry anthology.
  The correspondence files often contain other materials, such as solicited memoirs, photographs of correspondents, or printed materials that correspondents sent to Hubbell. Such materials have been filed under the name of the person who sent or wrote them. For example, letters exchanged between John Wheelock and Aubrey Burns are filed under the latter's name. An audio cassette recording of four of John Wheelock's poems set to music and performed by the Philadelphia Symphony Orchestra is included in Wheelock's "Clippings" folder. Folders occasionally include Hubbell's retrospective commentary on the correspondence or correspondents, for example, Hubbell's brief notes on his relationships with Van Wyck Brooks and Aldous Huxley. Most of the commentary was written in 1976 when Hubbell prepared his papers for donation to Duke University. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent, then chronologically within each folder.
  - Adams, Andy, 1924-1976 (Box 2)
  - Ade, George, 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - Aiken, Conrad Potter, 1924-1976 (Box 2)
  - Allen, Gay Wilson, 1933-1976 (Box 2)
  - Allen, William Harvey, 1925-1931 (Box 2)
  - Anderson, Charles Roberts, 1938-1973 (Box 2)
  - Anderson, Sherwood, undated (Box 2)
  - Atchison, Ray Morris, 1952-1976 (Box 2)
  - Auslander, Joseph, 1925-1927 (Box 2)
  - Austin, Mary Hunter, 1924-1925 (Box 2)
  - Baker, Karle (Wilson), 1922-1931 (Box 2)
  - Basler, Roy Prentice, 1932-1976 (Box 2)
  - Beaty, John Owen, 1938-1948 (Box 2)
  - Benét, Stephen Vincent, 1935-1936 (Box 2)
  - Benét, William Rose, 1920-1934 (Box 2)
  - Bennett, John, 1924-1931 (Box 2)
  - Benton, Richard Paul, 1968-1974 (Box 2)
  - Blair, Walter, 1946-1976 (Box 2)
  - Boatwright, Frederic William, 1928-1971 (Box 2)
  - Bond, George Doherty, 1930-1978 (Box 2)
  - Botkin, B. A., 1929 (Box 2)
  - Boyd, James, 1931 (Box 2)
  - Boyd, William Kenneth, 1928-1936 (Box 2)
  - Bradford, Gamaliel, 1924-1976 and undated (Box 2)
  - Braswell, William, 1954-1976 (Box 2)
  - Brooks, John Lee, 1928-1970 (Box 2)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1924-1976 (Box 2)
  - Brown, Frank Clyde, 1926-1943 (Box 2)
  - Brown, Herbert Ross, 1954-1978 (Box 2)
  - Bryan, William A., 1932-1951 (Box 2)
  - Bruccoli, Matthew Joseph, 1955-1979 (Box 2)
  - Burns, Aubrey, circa 1967-1978 (Box 3)
  - Bynner, Harold Witter, 1922-1933 and undated (Box 3)
  - Cable, George Washington, 1888 (Box 3)
  - Campbell, Killis, 1935 (Box 3)
  - Campbell, Walter Stanley, 1924-1932 (Box 3)
  - Canby, Henry Seidel, 1926-1945 (Box 3)
  - Carlock, Mary Sue, 1958-1978 (Box 3)
  - Carlson, Eric W., 1966-1976 (Box 3)
  - Chapman, John S., 1927-1978 (Box 3)
  - Charvat, William, 1947-1955 (Box 3)
  - Coad, Oral Sumner, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Coatsworth, Elizabeth Jane, 1925-1934 and undated (Box 3)
  - Coffin, Robert Peter Tristam, 1942 (Box 3)
  - Conkling, Grace Walcott (Hazard), 1924 (Box 3)
  - Cowley, Malcolm, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Cox, Headley Morris, 1956-1979 (Box 3)
  - Craigie, William Alexander, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Dargan, Olive (Tilford), 1931-1936 (Box 3)
  - Davidson, Donald, 1927-1965 and undated (Box 3)
  - Davis, Curtis Carroll, 1950-1976 (Box 3)
  - Davis, Richard Beale, 1961-1978 (Box 3)
  - DeVoto, Bernard Augustine, 1928-1937 and undated (Box 3)
  - Duke, Mary Lorraine, 1977-1979 and undated (Box 3)
  - Eidson, John Olin, 1954-1978 (Box 3)
  - Eliot, T. S., 1935-1958 (Box 3)
  - Emanuel, James, 1976-1978 (Box 3)
  - Farrar, John Chipman, 1922-1946 (Box 3)
  - Ferguson, Charles Wright, 1929-1965 (Box 3)
  - Few, William Preston, 1928-1936 (Box 3)
  - Fisher, Benjamin Franklin, 1969-1979 (Box 3)
  - Flanders, Bertram Holland, 1934-1944 (Box 3)
  - Fletcher, John Gould, 1924-1976 (Box 3)
  - Foerster, Norman, 1925-1971 (Box 3)
  - Frost, Robert, 1921-1974 (Box 3)
  - Gambrell, Herbert Pickens, 1928-1978 (Box 3)
  - Garland, Hamlin, circa 1925-1935 (Box 3)
  - Gates, William Bryan, 1964-1976 (Box 4)
  - Gilbert, Allan H., 1944 (Box 4)
  - Glasgow, Ellen Anderson Gholson, 1925-1938 (Box 4)
  - Gohdes, Clarence Louis Frank, 1927-1961 (Box 4)
  - Graves, Robert, 1925 and undated (Box 4)
  - Green, Claud Bethune, 1940-1978 (Box 4)
  - Green, Paul Eliot, 1924-1956 (Box 4)
  - Greever, Garland, 1929-1939 (Box 4)
  - Gross, Sarah Chokla, 1932 (Box 4)
  - Guilds, John Caldwell, 1960-1979 (Box 4)
  - Harris, Isabella D., 1937-1979 (Box 4)
  - Head, Eunice (Hammond) Tietjens, 1924 (Box 4)
  - Henry, David Dodds, 1976-1978 (Box 4)
  - Herron, Ima Honaker, 1933-1977 (Box 4)
  - Heywood, DuBose, 1924-1931 (Box 4)
  - Hibler, Leo von, 1949-1957 (Box 4)
  - Hofbauer, Rosa, 1950-1952 (Box 4)
  - Holman, Clarence Hugh, 1958-1978 (Box 4)
  - Holman, Harriet R., 1944-1978 (Box 4)
  - Hoole, William Stanley, 1929-1978 (Box 4)
  - Hosford, Hemphill, 1943-1976 (Box 4)
  - Howe, Edgar Watson, 1935 (Box 4)
  - Huxley, Aldous Leonard, 1937-1976 (Box 4)
  - Jones, Howard Mumford, 1928-1978 (Box 4)
  - Lanier, Henry Wysham, 1931 (Box 4)
  - Laverty, Carroll Dee, 1944-1976 (Box 4)
  - Leary, Lewis Gaston, 1949-1978 (Box 4)
  - Leisy, Ernest Edwin, 1925-1952 (Box 5)
  - Lindsay, Nicholas Vachel, 1924-1934 and undated (Box 5)
  - Lomax, John A., 1935 (Box 5)
  - Lowell, Amy, 1921-1976 (Box 5)
  - Mabbott, Maureen (Cobb), 1977-1979 (Box 5)
  - Mabbott, Thomas Ollive, 1944-1959 (Box 5)
  - McCain, James Allen, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - McDavid, Raven Ioor, 1940-1977 (Box 5)
  - McFee, William, 1928-1935 (Box 5)
  - McGinnis, John Hathaway, 1929-1942 (Box 5)
  - MacKaye, Percy Wallace, 1931 (Box 5)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1940-1963 (Box 5)
  - The MacMillan Company, 1920-1957 (Box 5)
  - Manning-Sanders, Ruth, 1926-1928 and undated (Box 5)
  - Martin, Willard Edgar, 1933-1945 (Box 5)
  - Masters, Edgar Lee, 1934 (Box 5)
  - Mencken, Henry Louis, 1924-1925 and undated (Box 5)
  - Monroe, Harriet, 1922-1927 and undated (Box 5)
  - Mood, Robert G., Jr., 1928-1978 (Box 5)
  - Moore, Rayburn Sabatzky, 1956-1977 (Box 5)
  - Morton, David, 1924-1925 and undated (Box 5)
  - Nakamura, Junichi, 1938-circa 1974 and undated (Box 5)
  - O'Neill, Eugene Gladstone, 1924 (Box 5)
  - Odum, Howard W., 1934 (Box 5)
  - Patton, Lewis, 1962-1965 (Box 5)
  - Paulovsky, Louis H., 1951 (Box 5)
  - Pearson, James Larkin, 1934-1979 (Box 5)
  - Perry, Bliss, 1922-1924 (Box 5)
  - Pinero, Sir Arthur Wing, 1927 (Box 5)
  - Pochmann, Henry August, 1966-1971 (Box 5)
  - Pound, Ezra Loomis, 1935 (Box 5)
  - Quinn, Arthur Hobson, 1927-1952 (Box 5)
  - Rachal, William M. E., 1955-1965 (Box 5)
  - Raetz, Martha, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
  - Ransom, John Crowe, 1924-1954 (Box 5)
  - Reese, Lizette Woodworth, 1924-1935 (Box 5)
  - Repplier, Agnes, 1935 (Box 5)
  - Rippy, James Fred, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Robbins, John Albert, 1967-1978 (Box 5)
  - Robert, Joseph Clarke, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Roberts, Elizabeth Madox, 1935 (Box 5)
  - Robinson, Edwin Arlington, 1921-1976 (Box 5)
  - Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1871-1964 (Box 5)
  - Rubin, Louis Decimus, 1955-1976 (Box 5)
  - Sally, Alexander Samuel, 1939-1942 (Box 5)
  - Sandburg, Carl, 1921-1975 (Box 5)
  - Sanders, Ottys, 1974-1978 (Box 5)
  - Sarett, Lew R., 1924-1926 and undated (Box 5)
  - Scollard, Clinton, undated (Box 5)
  - Shepard, Odell, 1934-1938 (Box 5)
  - Sinclair, Upton Beall, 1935 (Box 5)
  - Skinner, Constance Lindsay, 1925 (Box 5)
  - Smith, Garland Garvey, 1929-1978 (Box 5)
  - Smith, Henry Nash, 1928-1978 (Box 5)
  - Spiller, Robert Ernest, 1954-1976 (Box 6)
  - Sterling, George, 1924-1925 (Box 6)
  - Stewart, Randall, 1951-1959 (Box 6)
  - Stoddard, Hope, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
  - Stovall, Floyd, 1952-1977 (Box 6)
  - Stroven, Carl Gerhardt, 1932-1944 (Box 6)
  - Swett, Margery, 1924-1925 (Box 6)
  - Tate, Allen, 1940-1978 (Box 6)
  - Teasdale, Sara, 1924 (Box 6)
  - Thorp, Willard, 1946-1977 (Box 6)
  - Turner, Arlin, 1949-1977 (Box 6)
  - Untermeyer, Louis, 1922-1943 (Box 6)
  - Van Doren, Carl Clinton, 1919-1920 (Box 6)
  - Van Doren, Mark, 1929-1941 (Box 6)
  - Ward, Christopher, 1935 (Box 6)
  - Wells, Anna Mary, 1964-1976 (Box 6)
  - Wheelock, John Hall, 1920-1978 and undated
    - Correspondence, 1920-1978, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1971-1978 and undated, 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Widdemer, Margaret, 1925 (Box 6)
  - Wilt, Napier, 1939-1946 (Box 6)
  - Wister, Owen, 1931 (Box 6)
  - Woodress, James Leslie, 1946-1972 (Box 6)
  - Zeek, Charles Franklyn, 1929-1976 (Box 6)
- Correspondence by Date Series, 1919-1979, bulk 1929-1955
  [RESTRICTED. Contains recommendations. For a period of 75 years after the latest date in the collection, patrons must sign an Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form before using materials.]
  Contains single letters from publishers, colleagues, librarians, and minor writers. As in the Correspondence, Alphabetical Series, these letters pertain to the daily paperwork of academic life, such as departmental and committee appointments, recommendations, thesis approvals, and speaking engagements. Several letters concern Hubbell's writings and research.
  - 1919-1929 (Box 6)
  - 1930-1942 (Box 7)
  - 1943-1975 (Box 8)
  - 1976-1979 (Box 9)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1867-1998 and undated, bulk 1920-1979
  This series consists of two subseries, Writings by Hubbell and Writings by Others. Unpublished and published manuscripts, reprints, reviews, and correspondence pertaining to the writings make up each subseries. The materials in both subseries are arranged alphabetically.
  - Writings by Hubbell Subseries, 1908-1978 and undated, bulk 1920-1978